what are the implications of our fat
cells accumulating high levels of
cholesterol in this video I explore that
question while continuing to put a focus
on activities of the egg industry
[Music]
there's abundant evidence that dietary
cholesterol increases cardiovascular
disease risk the misdirection of the egg
industry focuses on fasting levels of
LDL cholesterol which are only raised by
about 10 percent however the main effect
of diet is on the postprandial State the
after-a-meal state for about four hours
after high fat high cholesterol meal
there's oxidative stress artery
dysfunction and arterial inflammation
which happens after eating more than 140
milligrams of cholesterol Which is less
than a single egg so while the egg
industry spends hundreds of millions
trying to convince people dietary
cholesterol is harmless there are good
reasons for limiting cholesterol intake
in persons at risk for vascular disease
but white vascular disease coronary
heart disease is our number one killer
of men and women so aren't we all at
risk yes it's seldom understood that
this essentially means all people in
developed countries who expect to live a
long life should cut down on eggs in
response the egg industry has
experimented with ways to reduce the
cholesterol content of eggs by for
example feeding laying hens cholesterol
lowering statin drugs or even techniques
to reduce cholesterol content in egg
yolks once the egg is formed using
things like a solvent extraction with
like fingernail polish remover acetone
however such methods have not been
scaled up due to reasons such as food
safety
or the Egg industry can spend its time
going after new plant-based competitors
like the company eat just
the USDA investigated allegations of
misconduct by the American egg board
which is run by the federal government
like the allegation that egg boards
staff threatened the CEO of eat just in
emails they exchanged about putting a
hit on him and indeed they discovered
emails including references such as can
we pool our money and put a hit on him
and having old buddies from Brooklyn pay
him a visit
what corrective actions did the USDA
take the American egg board has admitted
to the inappropriateness of such
comments and apologized and the Egg
board staff and board members will be
required to complete additional training
regarding proper email etiquette and
ethics
dietary cholesterol may also contribute
to inflammation in your body fat that
can spill over into your bloodstream
body fat is a major site for cholesterol
storage in humans your fat cells can
accumulate high levels of free
cholesterol which cannot be broken down
by cells and is toxic at high
concentrations
and that may lead to macrophage
accumulation here's our fat biopsy see
those little blue dots those are dying
macrophages which are type of immune
cells that can spill their contents of
inflammatory chemicals that are believed
to result in many of the metabolic
Arrangements that accompany obesity
including insulin resistance systemic
inflammation and atherosclerosis
so reducing excessive dietary
cholesterol intake is suggested as a
simple way to attenuate obesity
Associated metabolic diseases
yeah but has it actually been put to the
test and people we know dietary
cholesterol promotes the swelling of fat
cells and belly fat inflammation in
monkeys but that's like research showing
dietary cholesterol directly induces
acute intestinal inflammation in both
mice and zebrafish
what are you supposed to do with that
information there just weren't any human
studies
until
now vegetarians consume significantly
less cholesterol although eggs are the
single largest source of cholesterol in
the American diet more than any of the
individual types of meat meat in general
is the number one overall source with
more cholesterol coming from chicken
than from red meat researchers took
biopsies from the vegetarians and not
only did their fat average fewer than
half the pro-inflammatory macrophages
compared to biopsies taken from
omnivores the meat eaters had 50 greater
expression of tumor necrosis factor in
their abdominal fat which is a potent
inflammatory marker though there's lots
of stuff in meat besides cholesterol
that could have contributed to the
inflammatory state
but what else you need to know be on the
bump in heart disease risk preeminent
Harvard nutrition Professor Mark
hegstead once wrote that if cholesterol
were introduced as a new food additive
we would cite the evidence that it
raises cholesterol and heart disease
risk and the conclusion would almost
certainly be that cholesterol could not
be considered safe at any level because
any intake level above zero increases
the risk of our number one killer
disease
[Music]
thank you